Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1a; 4" height x 2" width x 1 1/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; The tablet has a small break and loss at one corner; the entire corner is not lost, as the loss is only visible on one face. Just below where the loss is visible, the face has a small spot with a dark black substance in it that may be fill. Further down, almost in the opposite corner, there is a round, pitted spot. The opposite face also has a round pitted spot that is close to one corner. The sides of the pitted spot are smooth enough that it may have been gouged out with an implenent of some sort. The color of the tablet is dark gray, except along one short end and one long side; those areas are pale tan. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from Iddin-Ninshubur to Suen-abi, and concerns a delivery of sesame and an ox to be handed over to third individual.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "ur"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-17; 1. 'Servant of knowledge' 2. 'Servant of flesh' 3. 'Servant of the smith'; 3 3/8" diameter x 7/8" depth, lentil; Lenticular tablet with two large clusters of mineral deposits: the first cluster is on the inscribed face and the second is partially on the edge and partially on the convex face. There is a loss along the edge near the second cluster. There is another loss at one area of the edge that extends across the surface on the convex face. There is a shallow loss at the center of the convex face, surrounded with scratch marks. It is unclear whether these were made while the clay was still wet or after the clay had dried as the entire tablet is a deep brown color. There are some other minor surface losses and scratches overall. (Drawer 5)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names that begin with "ur". This acrographic arrangment was popular among ancient Mesopotamian vocabularies.
- School text, literary exercise from Gilgamesh and the Bull of Heaven., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 129; 4" height x 2 3/4" width x 7/8" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet fragment that has broken into five pieces. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. This adhesive is visible in portions of the crack. There are deep crevices along the breaks due to several losses, particularly on the face with less cuneiform impressions. There is a large loss at one corner. An incomplete crack extends from one of the breaks on the face with more cuneiform impressions. There are two deep scores across one edge made by a modern implement. There are some minor surface losses throughout. A coating has been applied to at least a portion of the surface. (Drawer 6)
  This advanced student exercise is a literary excerpt from Gilgamesh and the Bull of Heaven. The text is signed by its scribe.
- School text, lexical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-7; 3 1/8" diameter x 7/8" depth, lentil joined from fragments with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet that has been broken approximately in half. The two pieces have been reattached with adhesive and the breaks have been filled with clay or clay-like substance. There is a small triangular loss near one end of the break on the surface of the flat face. That possibly was reattached or filled. There is a small loss on the edge at the other end of the break. About a quarter of the surface on the flat face has a sheen-possibly this is some coating or from wear. (Drawer 1)
  This beginner's vocabulary practice includes Akkadian term for ambidexterous, which has only two other attestations.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "ur"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-33; 5" height x 3 5/8" width x 1 3/8" depth, rectangular multi-column tablet; Rectangular tablet fragment with several losses. Two edges are jagged from uneven losses. Both of these edges have gouges made with modern tools, as well as deep crevices that have been covered with an adhesive. The other two edges also have some losses (not to the extent of the first two edges described) including some scratch marks along one of these edges. It is difficult to tell if these scratches were made while the clay was still wet or after the clay had dried. There are some patches on both faces where portions of cuneiform inscriptions are obscured. Possibly these are erasures that were made while the clay was wet (?) The tablet is a mottled brown and black color. There are white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 2)
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-2; 3 7/8" height x 2 5/8" width x 5/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; One face of the tablet is relatively flat and rectangular, but the other face appears to have been smashed inward toward center while the clay was still wet. As a result, that face is compressed upward with a groove in the middle. (Viewed from the short end, the tablet looks almost triangular.) On one side of the compresed face there is a deep but incomplete crack at one side. Part of the face closest to the edge has spalled along the crack. On the flatter face there is an area of spalling near one edge. This is old damage, as the spalled area has the same patina as the rest of the tablet. (Drawer 3)
  This student practice letter is written to Nibu from Naram-….
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1d; 3 1/2" height x 1 7/8" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; One face of the tablet has an old break and loss in two corners. Each of these small losses has the same patina as the rest of the tablet, indicating that the losses are ancient. The opposite face has a break and loss in one corner and an oval-shaped gouge close ot the middle. Tiny white particles scattered across both faces do not appear to be salt crystals. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is to Ibni-Ea from Tashin, ordering him to send various commodities.
- School text, literary exercise from Lipit-Eshtar B., Early Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900 BCE); SC-III-22; 1. The inner words, 2. You know its truth, 3. (king) Lipit-Eshtar.; 3 1/4" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil joined from fragments with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet that has broken into three pieces. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. Two of the pieces are much smaller -- the breaks are close to the edge of the tablet. Along one of the breaks, there is a chip at the edge of one of the breaks, as well as a few other small losses. There are incomplete cracks on both faces, but more on the convex face. There are two black spots on one part of the edge. There are other minor surface losses and scratched overall. (Drawer 5)
  This is an advanced student's exercise excerpt from Lipit-Eshtar's Praise in the Eduba. This exercise contains lines 32-33.
- School text, administrative exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 11; 3 1/2" height x 2 1/4" width x 7/8" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet; Tablet with two small gouged losses near diagonally opposite corners on one face. On the opposite face, a piece has cracked off one corner and is lost. About 2/3 of this face has been abraded (?) and is smooth. There are scattered black spost over all surfaces of the tablet. The tablet may be lightly coated. (Drawer 6)
  This is a basic student exercise in drafting administrative documents. The date of this text is given as Rim-Suen, year 20 (c. 1802 BCE).
- School text, lexical exercise of divine epithets., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 31718.1; 1. Ashgi of the animal pen 2. Ashgi of the long-lasting animal pen 3. Wise Ashgi; 3 1/4" diameter x 5/8" depth, lentil joined from fragments; A lenticular tablet that has been broken into at least six pieces and repaired with adhesive. The repairs are best viewed from the unincised face. This face has multiple losses and has adhesive residue on much of the surface as well as in cracks. The incised face has a strange surface texture, perhaps a light textile or finger print impression? There are two side-by- side gouges on this face that appear to have been made with a modern tool. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet contains a student exercise listing the epithets for the deity Ashgi.
- School text, legal exercise of a lawsuit., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-23b; 4 5/8" height x 2 1/8" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments with the reverse effaced; Rectangular tablet made of brown clay that has broken into three pieces. The three pieces have been attached with an adhesive. One of the breaks runs across the center of the tablet; the other break runs from one corner to the center. On the convex face, there are patches of adhesive visible along these breaks. On the same face are large losses along the crack, including one particularly deep loss close to the center. There are other, smaller losses visible overall on this face, creating a rough surface. It is unclear whether these losses are modern or ancient. There are some black patches and white accretions visible overall. (Drawer 2)
  This student exercise contains a lawsuit judgment between Ilaba-bani and Qurud-Ishtar. Qurud-Ishtar must compensate Ila-bani for poor wall maintenance that allowed Ila- bani's possessions to be stolen. This is a duplicate of 52174.23a
- School text, mathematical exercise of large numbers., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-7; 1 11/16" height x 2 11/16"width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; The tablet has a small loss along the edge of one face, continuing onto a short end. A short, incomplete crack is in the corner nearest that loss. A second corner on that face has an area of spalling. Just above the spalling is a small loss that continues onto a long side. The opposite face has a loss in one corner and a second, larger loss just above the diagonnally opposite corner. A third corner has an area of spalling. This spalling reveals clay that is a lighter brown color than the rest of the tablet, indicating that it is relatively recent damage. There are a few white spots scattered on both faces and on the long sides. (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise is a series of large numbers with no detectable relation to each other.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1g; 3 5/8" height x 2 1/16" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; This rectangular tablet has spalling on the corner of one long side; this area is covered with clear adhesive. At the opposite end of the tablet, the edge of one face and a portion of one short side is lost to spalling. The opposite face has three spots of spalling aong one long edge, and a fourth spot at the edge along one short side. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from Ur-Lisi to Ur-Kabta concerning agricultural matters.
- School text, legal exercise of a loan contract., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 2; 3 5/16" height x 2 3/8" width x 7/8" depth, red rectangular multi-column fragment; Rectangular tablet fragment with large losses. Two edges and a portion of a third edge are jagged from losses. There is a large loss to the surface of one face -- almost half of the depth of the tablet is missing in that area. The other face has a triangular loss on the surface near one corner. The remainder of one and a portion of another edge have some minor surface losses. A coating has been applied to the surface of the tablet. (Drawer 5)
  This student practice contract contains barley loans. The contents of the reverse is uncertain.
- School text., pre-Ur III; PARS 134; 1 7/8" height x 3 1/2" width x 15/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet fragment with losses to two of the corners. There are surface losses extending from one of the corner losses. The surface at these losses is uneven and jagged and there is some spalling. There are other minor surface losses and incomplete cracks overall. (Drawer 6)
- School text, grammatical exercise with the verb "to grow"., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.3; 1. Growing barley 2. Growing barley; 2 9/16" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; A small lenticular tablet with a large gouge and loss on the uninscribed (convex) face. The gouge was probably made by a modern tool when the object was excavated. This loss and gouge have no surface patina. There is a small, white paper label marked "3" adhered to the uninscribed face. (Drawer 1)
  This text contains a student's practice writing short sentences.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-15; Obverse 1. 'The sun god …'; 2. 'The sun god is exalted'; 3. 'The sun god is exalted'; 4. 'The sun god ..'; 5. 'The brother'; Reverse (unfinished); 2 9/16" height x 1 5/8" width x 13/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. There are considerable losses to one corner, especially on the face with only a few cuneiform impressions. There are a few other losses, both along edges. There are white concretions overall. There is a slight sheen to a portion of the surface on the face with more cuneiform impressions; possibly this is some coating. (Drawer 2)
  This beginner exercise is a student's practice writing personal names. The reverse is unfinished.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 90; 4 3/8" height x 2 5/8" width x 1" depth, baked red rectangular single column tablet; The tablet is mostly complete with only small losses to two corners. No adhesive appears to have been applied, but the surface may be coated with something. The tablet has multiple cracks, the most serious of which runs horizontally but is not broken across the entire tablet. (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise is practice in drafting a letter using the appropriate format and techniques. The text is dated, "11th day of the month Nenegar in the year Ami-ditana become king" (c. 1684). The letter was signed by scribes.
- School text, letter exercise for royal correspondence., Ur III- Old Babylonian Period (c. 2100-1600 BCE); SC-III-6; 3 7/8" height x 2 5/8" width x 1 1/8" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet with an ink mark "BF 8"; Rectangular tablet fragment with a loss all the way across one short side, and one lost corner. The remaining corner has a small gouge and loss on one face. That same face has a small spot of spalling near center. There are two small holes- each about the diameter of the head of a pin- toward one edge. The opposite face has several scattered deep cracks criss-crossing the surface. Many of these cracks continue onto one of the long sides of the tablet. One deep crack runs down the long side and through the center of the tablet to the other long side. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from from king Shulgi to Arad-mu. This exercise is signed by its scribe Sin-ishme'anni, dated on the 6th day.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 136; (Syllabary--no translation); 1 1/16" height x 7/8" width x 1" depth, baked small square prism (Drawer 5)
- School text, lexical exercise of wooden objects., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 92; 2 11/16" height x 2" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet inscribed on one face only. One corner of the inscribed face has been pushed inward; it appears that this compression took place while the clay was still wet. The uninscribed face has a long, diagonal gash near center, apparently the result of a modern tool strike. There is a chipped loss at the corner of the face near one end of this gash. A white circular sticker with "92." written in black ink was affixed to one short side of the tablet; the sticker has been removed. (Drawer 6)
- School text, lexical exercise for "if"., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.10; 1. if 2. if; 2 5/8" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil fragment with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet fragment has a large loss at one end. The edge at this loss is jagged and uneven. There is a gouge on this edge that most likely was made with a modern tool. There are several incomplete cracks on the uninscribed face -- possibly these are an indication that the surface on this face is starting to spall. There are some surface losses on this face, possibly from spalling. There are several white concretions visible overall. There is a small, cream-colored label with a typed number "10" adhered to the uninscribed face near the edge with the loss. (Drawer 1)
  This short exercise contains a student practicing writing "if".
- School text, administrative exercise of rations for weavers., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-28b; 4 3/8" height x 2" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet in good condition. There is an incomplete crack on one face that runs from one edge to its opposite edge. There are two minor surface losses on the flat face. One of these losses (closer to the center of the tablet) seems to have been made by a modern tool. There is some minor spalling and a shallow scratch on one edge. There are white concretions visible overall, though particularly on one side of the flat face. (Drawer 2)
  This basic student exercise contains a list of rations as payments to weavers. Administrative texts are the most prevalent and popular type of ancient Mesopotamian text, so the scribe need ample practice to master this genre.
- School text, administrative exercise and mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-35b; 3 1/4" height x 2 1/8" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet with transposed writing on the reverse; Rectangular tablet with a loss at one corner. There is adhesive covering a portion of this loss as well as some areas near the loss. There is an incomplete crack extending from this loss. There is a loss on one face with a patina similar to that of the rest of the face. It is possible this loss occurred while the clay was still wet. The other face has a small mound of clay at the center, surrounded by scrape marks. It seems that some of the scrape marks were made with an implement and others possibly were made by hand while the clay was still wet. There is an incomplete crack on this same face. There are some small scratches and wrinkles in the clay on the face -- some a result of scraping, also possibly made while the clay was wet. Notably, this face has a patina of a much darker brown-black. The other face is a medium brown color with patches of black and tan. There are other minor surface losses overall. There are some tan concretions visible overall, possibly this is dirt. (Drawer 3)
  This student tablet contains an administrative exercise for rations on the obverse and mathematic calculations transposed on the reverse
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-3; (Too broken to reconstruct); 3 1/8" height x 1 3/4" width x 1 1/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. These two pieces have been reattached with a white opaque adhesive as well as a clear adheseive, both of which are visible along the break line. The tablet is misshapen and twisted- as if it was pressed diagonally down the center. These are losses along the break as well as surface losses that look modern. A portion of the cuneiform script on one face has been erased, possibly from the pressing. There are a few incomplete cracks. There are some white concretions visible on one of the faces. (Drawer 4)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names. The substantial surface damage prevents an adequate reconstruction of the text.
- School text, mathematical exercise of surveying., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 68; 2 1/2" height x 1 3/4" width x 1/2" depth, red rectangular tablet; Small, flat, rectangular tablet that is mostly complete except for losses at one corner. One face of the tablet appears complete; the other face is damaged by losses and has five or six small, round holes punched into the surface. There are scattered tiny cracks on both faces of the tablet. The tablet appears to be coated with a glossy substance. Both faces have scattered grayish-black residue. (Drawer 5)
  This text contains a student's practice in surveying areas of land. This tablet includes a note from the scribe, "drawing of the lower part (of a field)."
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 29; 2 3/4" diameter x 13/16" depth, baked lentil with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet that has broken into four pieces. The four pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There is one main piece and three smaller pieces near the edge of the tablet. There are three losses along the edge of the tablet that look to have been made by a modern implement. There is a pit-like gouge close to the edge near the same spot on each face. There are several incomplete cracks overall on the flat face. There are groove marks overall on the surface, possibly made when the clay was still wet. There are some groove marks, which look similar to erasure marks, made by hand while the clay was still wet. The clay ranges in color from darker red-brown with some black patched to a lighter red-tan color. The three reattached pieces seem to be lighter in color on the convex face compared to the color of the largest piece. A coating has been applied to the surface of the tablet. (Drawer 6)
  This brief exercise is a student's vocabulary practice. The colophon on reverse enclosed in a rectangle, an unusual practice in ancient Mesopotamia.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Akkadian Period (c. 2340-2200 BCE); 38771; 2 1/4" height x 1 3/4" width x 1/2" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Small, rectangular tablet of light brown clay, inscribed on one face only. One corner of the tablet is lost, and this damage is visible on both faces. On the inscribed face, there is an area of spalling next to the lost corner that extends 2/3 of the way across the face. On the plain face, there is a deep, diagonal gouge next to the lost corner. At the opposite end of the plain face, there is a small, shallow gouge near the edge. There are several spots of dark brown discoloration on the plain face. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet is a student's practice at math problems.